Guide to the Frederick Townsend Ward Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frederick Townsend Ward papers
1862-1862
MS 1666
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The papers consist of correspondence and documents related to Frederick Townsend Ward's role as commanding officer of the "Ever Victorious Army" which helped crush the Taiping Rebellion in China (1850-1864). Material of a personal nature is minimal and pertains to his wedding arrangements.
Ward, Frederick Townsend, 1831-1862
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection, MS 352.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
"Devil Soldiers" and the "Ever Victorious Army." Ward, a naturalized Chinese subject, married Chang Mei, the daughter of a mandarin, in 1862. Ward died on September 22, 1862 in Ningpo from wounds suffered in battle.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence and documents related to Frederick Townsend Ward's role as commanding officer of the "Ever Victorious Army" which helped crush the Taiping Rebellion in China (1850-1864). Material of a personal nature is minimal and pertains to his wedding arrangements.
China -- History -- Taiping Rebellion, 1850-1864; Ward, Frederick Townsend, 1831-1862
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this collection are in Chinese. English summaries have been provided by the translators whose connection to Ward and the papers is undetermined. Summaries of these translations make up the folder titles.
  - A roll call: list of soldiers on board a steamer wherein is noted their presence, absence, state of health, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter wrapper [possibly from above item], 1862 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book explaining matters relating to the Military Board, the Board of Revenues and Board of Ceremonies, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter wrapper from [Ching Poo?], 1862 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Order of the Viceroy to the various commanders to send up reports on their troops, 1862 April (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Woo Tautae?] exhorts Ward to use his best endeavors with his men to protect Shanghai from the incursion of the rebels, and possible promotion, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Shanghai maritime inspection of the American ship, "Cricket", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Account of the manner of Ward's promotion to generalship, written by [Woo Tautae?], 1862 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Note from [Woo Tautae?] to Mr. Fitzroy making mention of cannon and cannon balls, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of names of soldiers, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified, 1862 April (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Certificate of promotion of [Hoo Chang Too?], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Travel pass issued by the T'ai-p'ing authorities to a "foreigner" to go from Chia-hsing to Shanghai for the purpose of conducting business (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Imperial edict discussing the possibility of rewarding/promoting Ward and Henry Burgevine for bravery in battle, 1862 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Travel pass to a foreigner, issued by a Taiping officer, Zhong Liangxiang, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Petition from the first and second columns of the Ever Victorious Army requesting perimission to accompany Ward back to Sung-chiang, 1863 Jun27-July 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter to Ward from Cheng Xueqi, colonel of the Hui Army, discussing his resources, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letter from Wu Hsu to Ward congratulating him on a victory, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Formal notes exchanged between the parents of bride and groom when a marriage is agreed upon [from Fan Sheng-fu to Ward], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Order to Ward from Li Hongzhang, acting governor of Jiangsu, to fight rebels, 1862 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letter from Wu Hsu to Ward expressing delight in Ward's victory against 30,000 rebels by 600 soldiers of the foreign-gun-troop, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Order from Wu Hsu to Ward asking Ward to send his armed ships to attack rebels in Dujiahang, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pass for a foreigner issued by an officer of Taiping, 1862 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Account of monies for soldiers, interpreters, drummers, and others, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letter from Wu Hsu to Ward to proceed to Ch'ing-p'u to fight the rebels and to abstain from entering the city after the expulsion of rebels to avoid criticism, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Note from Wu Hsu concerning customs, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letter from unidentified person informing Ward that the rebels have left, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Men's names, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)